（テンテン）いくわよ　リー。
Here I come, Lee!
（リー）いつでも。
I'm ready!
ハァ～ッ！
フッ！
表蓮華。
Primary Lotus!
どうよ？　限界以上の重さでしょ。
How's that?
It's heavier than what
you can handle, right?
うわぁ～っ！
リー。
Lee!
リー？
Lee?
さっさと出てきなさいよ　リー。
これくらいなによ！
Come up, Lee!
That was nothing!
リー！
Lee!
《昔の私が夢見ていたこと》
I used to dream about this
when I was a little girl.
綱手様っていうんだよ。
え？
Her name is Lady Tsunade.
すごい強いんだって。
そう　伝説のくノ一　綱手様。
They say she's really strong!
Yes! That's Lady Tsunade,
the legendary kunoichi!
決めた。　私　綱手様になる。
I've decided!
I'm going to become Lady Tsunade!
（ガイ）ついに今日からお前たちも
下忍になった。
From today, you are all genin.
そこでお前たちの目指すものを
聞いてみたい。
I want to take this time
to hear your goals.
（ネジ）答えたくない。
（ガイ）フム。
I don't want to answer that.
先生　たとえ忍術や幻術は
使えなくても→
Sensei!
I want to prove that even without
mastering ninjutsu or genjutsu,
立派な忍者になれることを
証明したいんです。
one can become a great ninja!
それが　僕のすべてです。
That is what I live for!
フッ。
君　何がおかしい！
Hey! What's so funny?!
お前　忍術も幻術も使えないって
時点で忍者じゃないだろ。
Listen, if you can't use ninjutsu
or genjutsu, you can't be a ninja.
なんだ？　バカか？
What? Are you stupid?
いや　熱血さえあれば
そうともかぎらないぞ。
No. That's not necessarily true,
if one has the passion.
ハハッ　よきライバルと青春し
競い合い高め合えば→
If you spend your youth
with a good rival,
sparring together
and honing your skills,
きっと立派な忍者になれる。
努力は必要だけどな。
there's no doubt
you will become a fine ninja.
But you will need determination.
はい。
うん。　で　君は？
Yes!
And you?
あっ　私は伝説のくノ一
綱手様になりたいです。
Oh, I want to become
the legendary kunoichi, Lady Tsunade!
あっ　エヘッ。
ibitsu na merodll de dekita aisareru beki ikimono da
Made from a distorted melody,
I'm a creature that should be loved
seika wa agerarenakute mo kokoro ga utatte iru kara
Even if I can't better myself,
I'll continue to sing from my heart
dore dake tsuyoi ame koete aisareru beki ikimono ka?
What storms must I overcome
To be a creature who should be loved?
yakusoku ga mamorenakute mo kokoro wa utatte iru kedo
Even if you can't keep your promise
My heart will keep on singing, but...
dono doa nokku shite aketara ii?
Which door should I knock on and open?
aketara doko e mukattara ii?
Once I open it, where should I go?
hitori ja kaerenai kara
I can't go home by myself
dareka o matte ita dake
I was just waiting for someone
kimi ga ima ichiban aitai hito wa dare?
Who is the one you want to meet the most?
kokoro no naka de dake hanaseru hito no kazu wa fuete iku
The number of people that I can only speak to in my heart
keep increasing
dakara tsuyoku naritakatta tada
So I just wanted to be strong
bokura mada yomitarinai monogatari
Our story just hasn't been told enough
muriyari owarenai koto wakattete
We know it's not something we can just quit
dare mo mina jibun no mama
Because we all want to be ourselves
tsuyoku naritakatta kara
We wanted to be strong
Ah, My Hero Lady Tsunade
Youth! Fight!
青春　ファイト。
（３人）ファイト。
– Fight!
綱手様か。
とにかく体術がすごかった。
LadyTsunade, huh.
Her taijutsu was simply amazing.
She has monster-like strength.
怪力の持ち主でな。
伝説の三忍の仲間→
There are rumors that she almost killed
her teammate Master Jiraiya,
自来也様を半殺しにしたという
噂もある。
who along with her was
one of the Legendary Sannin.
What must I do to become that strong?
どうしたら
そんなに強くなれるんですか？
Sheer determination!
努力あるのみ。
– Fight!
ファイト。
ファイト！
Fight!
1121! 1122!
１，１２１　１，１２２　１，１２３　１，１２４。
– 1123! 1124!
– Eleven hundred and...
– 1125, 1126!
１，１２５　１，１２６。
千百…。
1154, 1155!
１，１５４　１，１５５。
1156, 1157, 1158, 1159.
１，１５６　１，１５７。
ググ…。
１，１５８　１，１５９…。
1160!
やぁ～！
ぴゃ！？
Okay, Lee! Go!
（ガイ）よし　いけ！　リー！
はっ！　やぁ～！
（テンテン）ハァ…。
ん？
努力はしてるんだけどなぁ
全然　強くならない。
I'm trying my best,
but I'm not getting any stronger.
綱手様にたどり着くのに
どれだけ　かかるんだろう。
How long will it take to get
to Lady Tsunade's level?
ふむ…。
Lady Tsunade inherited
the talents of the First Hokage.
綱手様は　初代火影の
才能を受け継ぐお方だからな。
So are you saying talent is
more important than determination?
それって　努力より才能って
言ってませんか？
Oh no!
What I'm trying to say is
あ…　いやいやいや。
俺が言いたいのは→
that each shinobi is suited
to different things.
忍にも　それぞれ
向き不向きがあるということだ。
テンテンに怪力が身につくかどうかは
誰にもわからん。
No one can say whether
you will develop superhuman
strength or not, Tenten.
うわぁ～！
それまで。
Stop right there!
綱手様
怪力だけじゃないんですよね？
Lady Tsunade has more than
just monster strength, right?
Right. She is a specialist
in Medical Ninjutsu.
おう　医療忍術のスペシャリストだ。
どんな病気もケガも→
They say that there isn't an illness
or injury that Lady Tsunade can't heal.
綱手様に治せぬものは
ないという話だぞ。
私にも医療忍術を教えてください。
Please teach me Medical Ninjutsu!
まあ　俺の場合
医療忍術というか何というか→
Well, what I teach is a little different
from Medical Ninjutsu.
ちょっと違うんだな。
How do you do it?
どんなやり方ですか？
僕にも教えてください！
Please teach me too!
（ガイ）え？　おぉ。
う～ん　まあその…。
Yes, well...
なんだ　気合いと根性だ。
It's energy and guts!
Oh, that again.
な～んだ…。
だが　医療忍術を覚えたいという→
Still, I think you have passion
in wanting to learn Medical Ninjutsu!
テンテンの熱血は　すばらしいぞ。
これこそ青春！
That's the right spirit!
I will speak to
the Medical Corps for you.
医療班に
俺が話をつけておいてやろう。
やった～！
Yes!
上級医療技術の講義は　これまで。
That ends the lecture
on high-level Medical Ninjutsu.
では　実技に移りましょう。
はい！
We will now begin hands-on training.
All right.
医療忍術は　その名のとおり→
As its name suggests,
Medical Ninjutsu is ninjutsu used
in healing by controlling chakra.
チャクラをコントロールして
治療に使う忍術です。
はい。
Yes!
You use your own chakra to stimulate
the chakra network of your patient...
自分のチャクラで
相手のチャクラの経絡を刺激し…。
はい。
Yes.
細胞を活性化させ…。
and revitalize the cells.
はぁ～！
あ…。
君　たぶん…。
I think perhaps...
（テンテン）向いてないって言われた～。
I was told I wasn't suited for it!
（ガイ）ハハハハ！　まあ気にするな。
Well, don't let it bother you.
医療忍術が使えなくても
立派なくノ一は　いくらでもいる。
There are many fine kunoichi
who cannot perform Medical Ninjutsu.
では私は　伝説の綱手様のように
なりたいんです！
But I want to become like
the legendary Lady Tsunade.
Isn't there any other skill that
makes Lady Tsunade legendary?
他に何かないんですか？
綱手様の伝説。
う～む…　口寄せの術だな。
There is the Summoning Jutsu.
巨大なナメクジを口寄せする。
She can summon a giant slug.
That's why she was also
called the Slug Princess.
だから　ナメクジ姫などと
呼ばれたこともある。
The Summoning Jutsu?
口寄せの術？
あぁ　そうだ。
Yes, that's right.
口寄せの術って
どうすればできるんですか？
How do you do Summoning Jutsu?
あぁ　あれは
時空間忍術の一種だからな。
Well, it's a type of
Transportation Technique.
まず　その才能があるかどうかだ。
But first we have to see if
you have the skill to use it.
よし　いいな。　やってみろ。
All right, ready?
Try it.
はっ！
でた！
すごい！
Something appeared!
Amazing!
時空間忍術の才能は
あるようだな。
It seems you have the ability to do
the Transportation Technique.
うむ…　となれば→
Now, you need to enter into
a contract with the one you will summon.
口寄せする相手と
契約を結べばいい。
口寄せの術！
Summoning Jutsu!
ん～？
ガイ　これが　お前の生徒たちか？
Guy, are these your students?
It spoke!
しゃべった！
忍亀か。
A ninja tortoise?
さすが　ガイ先生です！
あの…　ナメクジは　いませんか？
Way to go, Guy Sensei!
– Umm...
– Huh?
You don't have a slug?
（ガイ）ナメクジより
カメのほうがいいだろう。
Isn't a tortoise better than a slug?
何じゃと　小娘！
わしの何が不満じゃ！？
What did you say, little girl?
Do you have something against me?
え～と…
伝説になってないとこかな。
Well, you're just not legendary,
I guess.
無礼者め！　契約など
こちらから願い下げじゃ！
Such insolence!
Well, I refuse to enter into
a contract with you!
い～だ！
Tenten, don't be so selfish!
テンテン　わがまま言うな。
It's not easy to find a partner
for a summoning contract!
口寄せの契約を
結んでくれる相手は→
そう簡単に見つかるもんじゃない。
え？　そうなの？
Oh? Is that so?
まぁ　それでも
練習は続けておくことだ。
Anyway, keep training!
Okay.
はい…。
他に綱手様の伝説はありますか？
Is there anything else
that Lady Tsunade is legendary for?
ん？
あとは伝説になるほど
酒と博打が趣味とか。
Well, her love of sake and
gambling is legendary.
However, you can't emulate that.
だが　それを真似てみてもなぁ。
KURAKU
SAKE
お前　女の子だろう。
ハハッ　無理だ　無理だ。　ハハハハ！
I mean, you're just a little girl.
It's impossible.
（テンテン）酒！
Sake!
The drinking age is twenty.
お酒は二十歳になってから。
ニャン。
ちょっと　離しなさいよ！　バカ！
Hey! Let me go! Stupid!
GAMBLING HOUSE
MARUSEI
ニャン！　ニャン！
I'm going to become just like
the legendary kunoichi, Lady Tsunade!
私は伝説の　くノ一
綱手様みたいになるんだから！
綱手様だと！？　だったら　もっと
大きくなってから来るんだな！
Did you say Lady Tsunade?
Then come back when
you're much bigger!
綱手様はな
伝説の巨乳の持ち主なんだぞ！
Lady Tsunade's big chest
is legendary!
伝説の…　巨乳…。
Legendary... big chest.
今日こそ
今日こそ勝ってみせますよ　ネジ！
Today is the day!
I'm going to beat you, Neji!
だぁ～！
ん？　どうした？　青春の悩みか？
What's the matter?
Something troubling your youthful heart?
あぁっ！
リー！　ほんと　あんたってば
懲りないんだから。
Lee, you never learn, do you?
勝てっこないでしょ！
ネジは　あんたと違って…。
You can't beat him!
Neji's not like you.
天才なんだから。
He's a genius.
リー！　出てきてよ！
Lee! Come up!
あんた
絶対あきらめないんでしょ！
You never give up, right?
Lee?!
リー！
Stop, Lee!
やめろ　リー！
こいつ　敵に操られているぞ！
He's being controlled
by the enemy!
Neji, find the user of the jutsu.
I'll stop Lee!
ネジは術者を捜せ！
リーは　俺が止める！
ギャパパパ～！
If you cannot use
ninjutsu or genjutsu,
（ネジ）忍術や幻術が使えなければ→
you'll definitely be susceptible
to an enemy's jutsu.
敵の術にかかりやすいのは当然だ。
（ガイ）うん。
It makes me uneasy to be on
the same team with someone like that.
そんなやつと
チームを組むのは不安だ。
うん…。
うぉ～！　おっ！？
No matter how hard I try,
I keep thinking,
いくら努力したって　僕は→
"What if I don't get any stronger?"
強くなれないんじゃないかって…。
It scares me so much
that I can't take it!
怖くて怖くて　たまらないんです！
If you don't have faith in yourself,
it's not worth the effort!
自分を信じないやつなんかに
努力する価値はない。
"Even if I can't do ninjutsu
or genjutsu,"
たとえ
忍術や幻術は使えなくても→
"I want to prove that
I can become a fine shinobi."
立派な忍者になれることを
証明したいんです…　ってな。
Isn't that your Ninja Way?
それが　お前の忍道だろ。
いい目標じゃないか。
I think that's a wonderful goal!
If you intend to take on ninjutsu
and genjutsu with only your taijutsu,
（ガイ）体術だけのお前が
忍術や幻術に対抗するなら→
you must perfect your taijutsu
so that it can be superior to them.
それを上回る体術を
身につけねばなるまい。
I am going to have you open up
to number five, the Gate of Closing,
（ガイ）八門遁甲を
第五の杜門まで開いてもらう。
of the Eight Inner Gates.
The Eight Inner Gates.
八門遁甲…。
術者の体を蝕む禁術ですか？
Is that the Forbidden Jutsu that
eats away at the body of the user?
I am prepared for this.
覚悟はできています！
その禁術を教えてください！
Please teach me the Forbidden Jutsu!
This is all for my dream!
すべては　夢のために！
♪～
あいや～！　とぉ～　とぉ～！
とりゃ～！
♪～
（テンテン）ちょ…　せ　先生！
Sensei!
（ガイ）ハハハハハ…。
Those are the rules!
ルールだからな。
It was decided that if I lose,
I would walk around the village
もし俺が負けたら　テンテンを乗せて→
逆立ちして　里を５００周するって
決めていたんだ。
on my hands 500 times
with you on top.
Oh boy. Please don't get me
involved with your silly made-up rules.
もう！　勝手に変なルール作って
人を巻き込まないでよ。
By the way, if you didn't win,
（ガイ）おう。　ちなみに
もし　テンテンが勝てなかったら→
my punishment for failing
to train you properly
指導が至らなかった罰として
ネジを乗せて→
was to hoist Neji up on top
and do 800 laps!
８００周するつもりだったんだがな。
ハッハッハッ！
It's amazing!
でも　すごいです！
Even if you had a handicap,
you made Guy Sensei lose!
ハンデがあったとはいえ
ガイ先生を負かすなんて！
あ…　私は
私のできることをやっただけよ。
I just did what I could.
ハハハハハ！
テンテンは　忍具のスペシャリストだな。
Tenten, you are a Ninja Tool specialist.
I'll say! Only Tenten
can battle like that.
えぇ！　あんな戦い方
テンテンにしかできませんよ！
Ninja Tools?
忍具の…　アハハ！
（テンテン）私は　忍具のスペシャリストだ！
I'm a Ninja Tool specialist!
Me... A Ninja Tool specialist?
Yeah right.
《テンテン：何が　忍具のスペシャリストよ…》
Next, please examine
my student Lee!
（ガイ）次こそは　次こそは→
我が弟子　リーを
見てやってください！
This way, Lady Tsunade!
こっちです！　綱手様！
On that day,
＜テンテン：その日　私は→
I saw the person I had admired
ever since I was little for the first time.
小さかった頃から
憧れ続けた人を初めて見て…。
And that person...
そして　その人は…＞
Forget about being a shinobi.
（綱手）もう忍は　やめろ。
Her words to Lee were like
a death sentence to him.
＜テンテン：リーにとっては→
死ねと言われるに
等しい言葉を宣告した＞
No. No, no, absolutely not!
違う…　違う　違う　断じて違う！
こんなことがあって
いいはずがない！
Something like this cannot happen!
Then does this mean that
determination means nothing?
やっぱり…。
努力なんて　無駄なのかな…。
やっぱり　才能がないと…。
（ガイ）テンテン。
Does it mean that if
you don't have talent...
Tenten!
リーの覚悟をナメるな。
Don't take Lee's resolve lightly.
お前のこれからと
これまでしてきた→
Nor your own resolve and passion
up to now, and beyond.
努力と熱血をナメるな。
The odds that the surgery will
be successful are 50% at best.
((綱手：手術が成功する確率は
たぶん　よくて５０％。
If it fails, you will die.
(失敗すれば…　死ぬ…))
But Lee, you underwent the surgery.
＜テンテン：だけど　リー
あんたは　その手術を受けた。
そしてすぐ
仲間を助けに行って…＞
And immediately afterwards,
you went to save our friend.
Guy Sensei! Tenten!
ガイ先生！　テンテン！
Lee! Lee, my boy!
リー！　リーよ！
You've recovered!
復活したな！
復活したんだな　リー！　リーよ！
You've bounced right back! Lee!
Yes! Guy Sensei,
thank you so much!
はい！　ガイ先生
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
（リー）ありがとうございます！
Lee!
リー！
You!
もう！
Lee!
リー！
You never give up,
no matter what!
《テンテン：どんなときでも
あんたは　あきらめなかった。
And because you always go for it,
あんたが頑張るから…
あんたに負けるもんかって→
I tell myself not to lose to you
and I'm able to give it my all too.
だから　私も頑張れたんだ。
Don't give up, Lee!
Don't lose to something like this!
負けないでよ…　リー。
こんなことで　負けないで！
Lee!
リー…　リー！》
《リー！》
ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
I was at my absolute limit.
限界ギリギリでした。
So did it work?
じゃあ　上手くいったの？
（リー）いえ　今までと同じです。
No, it was no different from before.
In order to move up a level
in the Eight Inner Gates,
八門遁甲　もう一段上げるには→
I need even more rigorous training.
もっと激しい特訓が
必要でしょう。
I sure could use
Guy Sensei's guidance right now,
ガイ先生の指導を仰ぎたい
ところですが→
but that's impossible right now.
今は　そうもいきませんし。
私でよければ　いくらでも…
つきあうけど…　何してるの？
If you're okay with me,
I'm happy to...
– One... two... three... four!
– help anytime.
– What are you doing?
– Five... six... seven!
あっ　おかまいなく
自分ルールですから。
Oh, don't mind me.
This is my own rule.
When intensive training doesn't work,
I make myself do 10,000 push-ups.
特訓に失敗したら　腕立て伏せ
１万回と決めていたんです。
– How long will that take?
– 17...18...19...
いつまでかかるのよ…。
１７　１８　１９　どうぞ　おかまいなく。
Just ignore me.
23...24...25...26...
２３　２４　２５　２６　２７　２８　２９　３０　３１
３２　３３！　うわぁ～っ！
27...28...29...
30...31...32...33...
テ　テ　テンテン…　重い…　重いです！
T-Tenten...
Heavy, so heavy!
Hey! You're making it sound
like I'm heavy!
ちょっと～！　その言い方だと
私が重たいみたいじゃない！
You should say, "The metal doll
you brought out is heavy, so heavy."
「テンテンの出した　金属の人形が重い
重いです」と言いなさい！
Say it.
You're so rude.
ほんと　失礼なんだから！
《私はもう　綱手様のように
なりたいなんて思わない。
I no longer wish to be like
Lady Tsunade anymore.
But I haven't given up my dream
to become a legendary kunoichi.
でも…　伝説のくノ一になる夢は
まだ　あきらめてはいない》
fight!!
furishiboru dake sa saigo no itteki mo
I'm going to squeeze it down to the last drop
muda ni dekinaikara now is the time to go
Because I can't waste any of it, Now is the time to go
ikudo tsuma tsukimi to egaita yume wa
The dream that I created many times with you
ima koe kuma atte munune o sasu
I can now put it to words and it pierces my heart
it's not crazy
fight and fight, try and try for you
forever
kimi wa hitori janai
You are not alone
namida koete
Get over the tears
kimi to susunde ikou
I'll keep moving forward with you
nani mo kowaku narute na ii na
I'm not afraid of anything
this is the place to try
soshite bokura kitto tsunaida te o
I'm sure we'll never let go
kesshite hanasanaide asu e kakeru
Of each other's hands as we head for tomorrow
let's sing loudly
we are the one for the future
Next Episode
I was just taking a walk to see how things were going in the village.
Your argument reminds me of Naruto and Sakura.
（美空）　皆様
お変わりございませんか？
美空ひばりです。
Sakura's hit me like that before too.
では　最後まで
ごゆっくり　お楽しみください。
What? Well, they're more like comrades than friends.
You're asking me what the difference between a comrade and friend is?
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "Sai's Day Off"
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。
Sai's Day Off
That's a difficult question.